we have seen a road based processor but
this processor has not been a
superscalar processor it was only
issuing one instruction per cycle and
even though we have seen a variant in
one of the quizzes that commits up to
two instructions per cycle the
bottleneck will still be the issue so
now let's look at the real superscalar
processor what does it have to do first
it needs to fetch more than one
instruction per cycle
when we are fetching we are really
fetching more than one instructions
worth of memory per cycle so if our
instructions are for example four bytes
and we want to fetch to our fetch really
needs to supply us with eight bytes
every cycle then we need to decode more
than one instruction per cycle this
amounts to basically having more than
one decoder so every cycle the first
decoder will be looking at the first
instruction while the second one it will
be looking at the second instruction we
fetch etc next we have to issue more
than one instruction per cycle remember
that we need to issue instructions in
order so every cycle we will consider
the next instruction that should issue
for issuing and if it can issue we will
also consider the next instruction and
if that one can issue we will consider
the next one and so on so for example if
you are trying to issue up to three
instructions per cycle they still need
to be three consecutive instructions and
if one of them cannot issue then the
following ones cannot issue either we
want to be able to dispatch more than
one instruction per cycle we have seen
that if we have more than one execution
unit we actually can dispatch one
instruction to each of the units
effectively we will already able to
dispatch more than one instruction per
cycle
now the problem usually is that you have
many more ads than multiplies for
example so if you really want to finish
more than one instruction per cycle and
do that over many cycles probably we
would have to have something like to add
units and a multiplication unit so that
even if we have only ads to do we would
be able to issue and dispatch to per
cycle on average then we need to be able
to broadcast more than one result per
cycle this involves not only having to
broadcast buses or three broadcast buses
but also every reservation station has
to compare its tags that its waiting for
to every one of the buses because in any
given cycle we could have any of the
buses producing our results so this
immensely complicates reservation
station basically the cost of each
reservation station is proportional to
the number of broadcasts we have to
monitor
if we had one let's say that some cost
having three broadcasting said is going
to be at least three times as costly and
finally our commit logic needs to be
capable of committing more than one
instruction per cycle we have already
seen in one of our quizzes that this is
very similar to issuing in that for
committing with we consider the first
instruction that is not committed for
commit if that one can commit we can
consider the next one to commit in the
same cycle and so on so it's not only
that we have to consider three
instructions for commit and check
whether they are done we also have to
make sure that we don't commit for
example the third instruction we are
considering unless both of the previous
ones are committed and among these we
really have to be worried about the
weakest link meaning if we can fetch up
to let's say four instructions per cycle
the code up to four instructions per
cycle is shown only one per cycle
dispatch up to four broadcast up to four
and commit up to four we will still be
limited by the issue of only one so on
average we can never produce more than
one instruction finishing per cycle and
committing because simply they have to
go to issue one at a time if all of
these are very very large and one of
them is limited to let's say three then
again we will not be able to average
more than three instructions per cycle
no matter how well the program is
matching this organization so pretty
much this is kind of like a pipe where
the width of the pipe in each of the
stage is determining the flow of the
entire pipe pretty much the narrowest
place in the pipe is what limits the
flow of the instructions through it